-= 奇遇电影字幕组|QY-045 =-
更多佳片请关注官方公众号 Cinematik
翻译｜@月球怪物　@Sherlock3003　@movie404
校对｜@門下走狗- 　@Whale(独立翻译)
字幕转制｜天外生物
感谢原字幕制作者
夏洛特·兰普林
汤姆·康特奈
45周年
走吧 麦克斯
Come on, Max.
- 早上好 梅瑟夫人  - 喔 克里斯
- Morning, Mrs Mercer.  - Oh, Chris.
你今天起得真早
You're early this morning.
我天刚亮的时候就被双胞胎吵醒了
I've got the twins waking me up at the crack of dawn.
我的天 我都忘了
Oh, my God, I completely forgot.
- 恭喜  - 谢谢
- Congratulations.  - Cheers.
- 你们俩日子怎么样？  - 事情多得可怕
- How are you both coping?  - It's a hell of a lot of work.
那是肯定了
I don't doubt it a second.
但你没问题的 你是个能干的小伙子
But you'll be fine. You were always a capable young man.
你现在一定很兴奋吧
You must be getting excited.
- 周六 对吧？  - 别提了 还有一堆事情要做
- Saturday, isn't it?  - Don't remind me. So much work to do.
不过 没问题的
Yeah, it'll be fine.
- 祝你好运  - 谢谢
- Good luck.  - Thank you.
我真为你们俩高兴
And I'm really over the moon for both of you.
- 谢谢 梅瑟夫人  - 凯特 叫我凯特就好
- Thank you, Mrs Mercer.  - Kate. Call me Kate.
我们已经不是在学校里了
We're not at school any more.
好的
Will do.
[The Platters 为美国黑人摇滚乐队]
[代表作《Only You》、《Smoke Gets in Your Eyes》]
你觉得 Platters 那首歌怎么样？
What do you think of that Platters song?
[The Platters 为美国黑人摇滚乐队]
[代表作《Only You》、《Smoke Gets in Your Eyes》]
- 什么怎么样？  - The Platters 的歌
- The what?  - The Platters song.
什么时候放？
What for?
跳第一支舞时放
First dance.
还是你觉得我们婚礼上放的歌已经过时了？
Or think it's a bit naff to have the same song we had at our wedding?
不 这首歌很可爱
No. Lovely song.
- 我一直都很喜欢  - 我就知道
- I've always liked it.  - Yeah, I know.
♫ 人们曾经问我怎知 ♫
♪ Asked me how I knew ♪
♫ 我的爱情意真挚 ♫
♪ My true love was true ♪
- 这是什么？  - 一封信
- What is it?  - A letter.
嗯 我知道 谁寄的？
Yes, I know, but who from?
- 用德文写的  - 是啊
- It's in German.  - Yeah.
写的什么？
What's it say?
我记不清这些动词啊名词啊的意思了 但是…
Well, I can't remember the verbs as well as the nouns, but...
但我想上面写的是他们找到她了
but I think it says they've found her.
找到谁？
Found who?
唔 准确说 是她的尸体
Well, her body, anyway.
天呐 是谁？杰夫
God, who? Geoff.
他们找到了卡佳
T-They've found Katya.
噢
Oh.
你知道我在说谁吗？
Y-You know who I'm talking about, don't you?
当然
Of course.
因为 我记得我和你说过 一清二楚
'Cause, I-I remember telling you, clear as day.
我当然记得 我是说 这是很久以前的事了
Of course I remember. I mean, it was a long time ago.
我就知道我和你说过我的卡佳
Yeah, I-I know I told you about my Katya.
她在那儿五十多年了 就像在冷冻库里一样
She's been there over 50 years, like something in the freezer.
现在他们找到她了
Now they've found her.
[图伦男子：自然环境下形成的木乃伊，死于公元前四世纪却在一九五〇年才被发现]
就像那个 呃 瑞典沼泽里的图伦男子
L-Like that, er, Tollund Man in the Swedish bog.
其实是在丹麦被发现的
Well, Danish, actually.
- 嗯？  - 写进课本里好多年了
- Hm?  - It was on the curriculum for years.
我给三年级生教过这些
I taught it to the third-formers.
我再去泡点茶
I'll make some more tea.
嗯 我还需要一本字典
Yeah, I'm going to need a dictionary.
我不知道去哪找
I-I don't know where to look.
你为什么不看看塑料箱子里呢？
Why don't you check in the plastic boxes?
什么也没有 除了DIY书
Nothing. Nothing but "do-it-yourself" books.
就是这个
That's it.
是它
Yeah.
啊 谢啦
Ah, thank you.
你看 现在是雪全都融化掉了
You see, what's happened is the snow has completely melted.
只剩下了冰
All that's left is the ice.
他们就是这么找到她的
A-And that's how they found her.
- 什么意思？  - 就是 她还在那儿
- What do you mean?  - Well, she's still there.
- 冻在冰里？  - 是的
- In the ice?  - Yeah.
顺流下来了一些 可以肯定 但那儿的水非常清澈
Way down, I'm sure, but the water is very pure up there.
一定是这样 所以他们才能看见她
It must be, so they can see her.
- 他们把她弄出来了吗？  - 还没
- Well, haven't they taken her out?  - Not yet.
为什么？
Why not?
你想 她可是被冻在瑞士雪山的冰川里 凯特
Well, she's in a glacier in the Swiss mountains, Kate.
这可没那么容易
It can't be that easy.
根本没有公路上去
There are no roads up there.
那他们怎么确定那个人是她？
So, how do they know it's her?
我是说 可能根本就不是她
I mean, it might not be her at all.
唔 我猜 根据事发地点 他们推测这个人是她
Well, they've made an assumption, I suppose, from where they found her.
可能他们从衣物分辨出是她
Maybe they can tell from what she's wearing.
从她的衣物？
From what she's wearing?
噢 对 对 对 那些 飞行员… 冰岛的 应该是
Oh, yeah, yeah, th-those, er, airmen in... Iceland, I-I think it was
他们被保存得很完好
they were perfectly preserved.
噢 我居然忘了
Oh, I don't remember that.
我看过这方面的资料
Yes. I saw a documentary on it.
他们因为被迅速冰冻 和死前看上去一模一样
They were the same as when they died because of how quickly they froze.
你觉得是这么回事吗？
And you think that's what's happened?
嗯… 我不知道 但你可以想象
Well, I don't know, but you can imagine.
我不确定她也是那样 毕竟过了这么久
Not sure it works like that. Not after all this time.
不过那样会很奇怪吧？
How strange would that be, though?
她看着还是一九六二年那样
She'll look like she did in 1962.
而我已经成了这副样子
And I look like this.
这是怎么啦？
What is it?
呃 别生气 凯特
Er, don't be cross, Kate.
我要出去抽支烟
I'm going to have a smoke.
- 你还好吗？  - 嗯
- Are you all right?  - Fine.
把这个吃了 然后去吃药
Please eat this. And take your pills.
他们在信里问我是否想去瑞士
Th-They've asked if I want to go to Switzerland.
他们为什么问这个？
Why would they ask that?
嗯… 去确认尸体
Well, to see the body.
- 什么时候？  - 越快越好吧 我猜
- When?  - Soon, I suppose.
- 你不打算去吗？  - 不知道
- You aren't thinking of going?  - Don't know.
大老远去瑞士？
All the way to Switzerland?
也不是很远
It's not that far.
有从斯坦斯特德机场起飞的航班
There are flights from Stansted.
是 但也够远的了
Yeah, but it's far enough.
- 你觉得我不应该去？  - 说实话？
- You don't think I should?  - Honestly?
嗯 不应该去
Well, no.
我不知道去的意义何在
I don't see the point.
- 再说我们在周六还有派对  - 我又不是说现在就走
- Plus we've got the party on Saturday.  - I wasn't thinking of going now.
- 我不会现在就走的  - 是啊 但你一定会去
- I-I wouldn't go now.  - Yeah, but still.
我不赞成你去爬那该死的大雪山
I don't like the idea of you climbing a big bloody mountain.
嗯 我觉得不会要爬山的
Well, I don't think it would come to that.
你连跟我一起去布罗茨散步都不愿意
You don't like going for a walk with me on the Broads
那地方可是跟煎饼一样平
and that's as flat as a pancake.
我知道
I know.
我说啦 凯特 不会要爬山的
Like I said, Kate, it wouldn't come to that.
可还是…
But still...
- 你不是要去镇上吗？  - 哦 我可以再找时间去
- Don't you have to go into town?  - Oh, I can rearrange.
别 你还是快去吧
No, y-you should go.
这事有点令人震惊 但仅此而已
It's been a bit of a shock, that's all.
我没事儿
But I'm fine.
- 你确定吗？  - 是的 很好
- Are you sure?  - Yeah, positive.
看起来大不一样了 空荡荡的
Oh. It looks different, all empty.
桌子一般放在这儿
Well, this is where the tables are usually placed.
主桌在这里 好让所有人都看得到你
The top one over there, so that everyone can see you.
谢了 但我们不需要主桌
We won't be having a top table, but thank you.
真的？
Really?
在这样的场合一张主桌是极妙的
A top table is so lovely at an event like this.
你们俩就是全场焦点
The two of you as a focal point of the room.
我们并不是要再来一次婚礼
We're not trying to recreate the wedding.
就是个派对
It's just a party.
好吧 当然 随你心意
Yes, well, it's your choice, of course.
这地方棒极了 对周年纪念来说 绝对是个明智的选择
I will say, though, it's a wonderful place, location-wise, for an anniversary.
这是四十周年 是吧？
It's your 40th, isn't it?
四十五周年
45th.
这可是个不太寻常的庆祝节点
That's an unusual one to celebrate.
我丈夫当时生病取消了四十周年纪念 所以我们不得不改变计划
My husband was ill and our 40th was cancelled, so we had to rearrange.
那么 我必须得尽量把这次办得非常特别 对吧？
Well, I must try and make this one super-special, then, mustn't I?
这儿绝对是举行周年纪念的绝佳地点
And this really is a great venue for such an event.
充满历史气息 是吧？
So full of history, you see?
像历久弥新的婚姻
Like a good marriage.
[特拉法尔加海战为英法两国的海上大战，最终英方取胜]
你知道特拉法尔加庆祝舞会就是在这里举行的吗？
Did you know that the Trafalgar Ball was held here?
知道 你的助手和我说了
Yes, your assistant told me.
那是一八〇五年
It was in 1805.
你能想象当时的场景有多么壮观吗？
Can you imagine how incredible that must have been?
[特拉法尔加战役：英国海军历史上最大的一次胜利]
[为英国奠定海上霸主的地位，但主帅纳尔逊被俘]
在场的每个人都盛装出席 庆祝这一伟大的胜利
Everyone here, dressed in their finest, celebrating such an achievement.
纳尔逊不是被杀了吗？
Wasn't Nelson killed?
但是我们赢得了战役啊
But the battle was won.
非常值得庆贺 不是吗？
And that has to be worth celebrating, doesn't it?
我们的婚礼上有主桌 但是我们一点也不喜欢
We had a table at our wedding, a top table, but we didn't like it at all.
我丈夫认为这是腐朽的资产阶级糟粕
My husband thought it a horribly bourgeois tradition.
我们看看开胃菜菜单吧？
Shall we have a look at the canapé list?
呃 好的 当然
Er, yes, indeed.
我马上回来
I'll be right back.
不急
No rush.
这里是杰夫和凯特的家 请留言
You have reached Geoff and Kate. Please leave a message.
你已经很久不听这首歌了
You haven't listened to this for a long time.
- 你感觉怎么样？  - 我很好
- How are you feeling?  - I'm fine.
你的手指怎么了？
What have you done to your finger?
噢 嗯 我只是 呃… 想修理一下马桶 结果 呃 把自己大拇指给割了
Oh, yeah, I was, er... trying to mend the lavatory and, er, well, I cut me thumb.
你把它修好了吗？
Did you manage to fix it?
我想它需要一个新的浮球阀
It needs a new ballcock, I think.
- 我之前打电话给你了  - 你留言了吗？
- Tried calling earlier on.  - Did you leave a message?
没 我就是想问问你还好吗
No, I just wanted to check you were all right.
好
Right.
[索伦·奥贝·克尔凯郭尔为丹麦基督教思想家，存在主义先驱]
- 你在看什么？  - 克尔凯郭尔
- What are you reading?  - Kierkegaard.
[索伦·奥贝·克尔凯郭尔为丹麦基督教思想家，存在主义先驱]
天呐 你又在尝试看这本吗？
Gracious, are you having a go at that again?
那本书你已经有三个不同版本了
You know, you have three editions of that book,
而且我觉得不管哪一版你连第二章都没读完过
and I don't think you've got past chapter two in any of them.
真是奇怪的一天
Yeah, it's been an odd day.
是啊
It sure has.
我就是… 呆在家
I just, er... stayed at home,
你知道的 和浮球阀作斗争
you know, grappling with the ballcock.
但你是对的
But y-you're right.
我都不怎么去散步了
I hardly go walking any more.
今天天气好 所以我出去了
And it was a nice day, so off I went.
- 那么你去哪儿了？  - 就去了村子里
- So, where did you go?  - Just to the village.
去买烟？
To buy cigarettes?
我还没嗅觉失灵呢 你知道吧？
I haven't lost my sense of smell, you know?
我只是不希望我们又开始抽烟
I just don't want us to start smoking again.
不 我不会 我不会的
No, I-I won't, I won't.
我保证
I promise.
好吧 继续说
OK. Go on.
我到了村子里 不知道怎么了
So, I was in the village, and I don't know what happened
遇见那个种族主义者从社区中心走出来…
but that racist from the community centre...
嗯哼 桑德拉·威尔金斯
Mm. Sandra Wilkins.
对，是她
Yeah, her.
她向我走来 正对着我
She came up to me, right up to me face,
然后不断问我是否还好
and she kept asking me if I was all right.
我说是的 但她不相信我
And when I said I was, she wouldn't believe me.
况且… 我什么也没做
And... l wasn't doing anything.
什么也没做 就是坐在鸭子池边的长凳上
Nothing. Just sitting on the bench by the duck pond,
想点自己的事 呼吸点新鲜空气
minding me own business and getting some air.
就是这样
All done.
我就做了这些 我保证
All I was doing, I promise.
我相信你
I believe you.
她是个可怕的女人
She's a dreadful woman.
- 别管她就是  - 嗯
- Just ignore her.  - Mm.
这菜还行吧？
Is it all right?
很好吃 很好
Oh, it's great. Great.
嗯
Yeah. Mm.
再来一杯？
A drop more?
嗯 谢谢
Mm, thank you.
- 怎么了？  - 没事
- What?  - Nothing.
- 我有些事想跟你说  - 说吧
- There's something I want to tell you.  - OK.
知道吗 我很确信我之前跟你说过了
You know, I-I feel sure I've told you before,
但那是很久之前了 所以 我有可能记错了
but it was a long time ago, so, I mean, I could be wrong.
- 嗯 说吧  - 好
- OK, go on.  - Yeah.
我算是她的直系亲属
Um, I-I was her next of kin.
什么意思？
What do you mean?
唔 从官方上来说
Well, officially.
我算是她的直系亲属 我确定之前和你说过的 凯特
I-I was her next of kin. I'm sure I told you this before, Kate.
我想我会记得我丈夫是另外一个女人的直系亲属这种事的
I think I would remember my husband being another woman's next of kin.
- 为什么？  - 什么为什么？
- Why?  - Why what?
为什么你算是她的直系亲属？
Well, why were you her next of kin?
因为他们觉得我们已经结婚了
Because they thought we were married.
- 谁？  - 官方 人们
- Who did?   - The authorities. People.
他们为什么会这么认为？
What made them think that?
我们跟他们是这么说的
We-We told them we were.
但你们没有 对吧？
You weren't, though?
噢 没没没 没有 当然没有
Oh, no, no, no. No, h-hell, no.
我们必须假装 这样别人才会让我们借住他们的房子
We just had to pretend, so people would let us stay in their houses.
那会儿和现在不一样 凯特 然后… 就是那场事故
Different in those days, Kate, and then after... the accident.
你没骗我？
You're not lying to me?
没有 凯特 她手上戴了一个戒指
No. Kate, she wore a ring on her finger.
小巧的木制戒指 像窗帘环一样 橡木制的
It was a small wooden ring, like a curtain ring, made of oak.
你还记得这些细节 真有意思
Funny you'd remember that.
那不算是真的
Well, it wasn't real.
好吧 你可以… 你可以早点告诉我的 杰夫
OK, you could've... you could've just told me, Geoff.
我以为我已经说过了
I thought I had.
如果我还没说 那么 这挺难的 呃…
If I hadn't, well, it's hardly, er...
把这种事告诉
the sort of thing you tell
你漂亮的新女友 不是吗？
your beautiful new girlfriend, is it?
我可不这么觉得
I suppose not.
我想我要… 上楼去然后洗个澡了
I think I'm going to have a... go upstairs and have a bath.
明天还有很多事要做呢
I've got lots to do tomorrow.
- 你确定你还好吗？  - 嗯 嗯
- Are you sure you're all right?   - Yes. Yes.
嗯 真的 挺好的
Yeah, really, I am.
我不能为咱们相遇之前发生的事生气 不是吗？
I can hardly be cross with something that happened before we existed, can I?
也不是这么说
Not really.
但是…
Still...
我想你现在都不愿意抱我了吧
I suppose a cuddle's out of the question.
我甚至觉得当时在那儿的根本不是我
It doesn't even feel like it was me that was there.
你明白我的意思吗？
Do you know what I mean?
你在那待了多久？
How long had you been up there?
六周还是七周吧 估计
Oh, six or seven weeks, I suppose.
或许更久
It seemed a lot longer.
我们出发时带了张地图
We had a map, er, to start with.
那玩意真他娘的不靠谱
It was so bloody unreliable.
不过我还是到了一个地方
I've still got it somewhere.
我们往山上更高的地方爬去
Yeah, we were getting higher into the mountains
我觉得最好得找个人
and I decided it would be best if we found someone,
你知道的 帮我们到意大利边境
y-you know, to help us get to the Italian border.
- 一个导游？  - 对 但不是真正的导游
- A guide?  - Yeah, wasn't really a guide.
[杰克·凯鲁亚克：美国著名小说家，代表作《在路上》]
这个黑皮小杂种觉得自己是杰克·凯鲁亚克
This swarthy little bastard who thought he was Jack Kerouac.
[杰克·凯鲁亚克：美国著名小说家，代表作《在路上》]
- 你一直都特讨厌凯鲁亚克  - 是啊 没错
- You always did hate Kerouac.  - Yes, I did.
也许你就是嫉妒了
Maybe you were jealous.
- 什么 嫉妒杰克·凯鲁亚克？  - 嫉妒那个导游
- What, of Jack Kerouac?  - Of the guide.
他在和她调情吗？
Was he flirting with her?
嗯 他们是有 呃… 在言语上
Well, they did have, er... the language.
我的德语 不那么好 带口音
My German, it wasn't that great, what with its accent.
他们常常笑话这个
They laughed a lot.
他永远只会开一些我不知道有什么好笑的玩笑
He was forever making these jokes I didn't get.
- 天呐 你可不喜欢这样  - 不 我不喜欢
- Oh, God, you wouldn't like that.  - No, I didn't.
他们一起在我前边走着 比必要的距离更往前
They were walking up ahead, more than they needed to perhaps,
或许… 我就随他们去了吧 我不知道
or... maybe I just let them, I don't know.
我们到了一个沿着岩石的小道
We were on a track round this rock,
冰川就在我们的右下方
and the glacier was on the right, below us.
我们沿路而下
Way down.
景色宜人
Beautiful thing, it was.
你会喜欢那儿的风景的 凯特
You'd love the landscape out there, Kate.
- 你真的会喜欢的  - 嗯 我相信
- You really would.  - Yeah, I'm sure.
他们离开了我的视线 走到了拐角处
They were out of sight, round the corner,
我最后听见的是她的笑声
and the last sound but one that I heard was her laughter.
天呐 这笑声真是让我恼火
And, Christ, did it annoy me.
但是不久 就传来了尖叫声
But then, there was a scream.
但这叫声并不响
It wasn't a loud scream, neither.
我估计是空气从她受到冲击的肺里倾泻而出
Sort of outpouring of air from her lungs from the shock, I suppose.
很低沉的喉音
It was low and guttural,
根本不像她的声音 柔软的 尖尖的
not like her voice, which was soft, higher-pitched.
天呐 太可怕了
God, that's just horrible.
嗯 嗯
Mm. Mm.
然后呢？
And then what?
就这样 无力回天
That was it, really.
等我到那里 她已经不见了
When I got there, she'd gone.
凯鲁亚克朝着那个洞望去
And Kerouac was looking down this hole.
一条裂缝
A fissure.
是的 裂缝 可以这么说 就像一块岩石从中间裂开
Yeah, a fissure, I suppose you'd call it, like a narrow, narrow crack in the rock.
你还记得在苏格兰那个吗？
D-Do you remember that one in Scotland?
- 嗯 我记得  - 对 就跟那个一样
- Yeah, I do.  - Yeah. Well, it was like that one.
- 嗯  - 只是深得多
- Yeah.  - Only much deeper.
凯鲁亚克就站在那里
And Kerouac was just standing there.
他的脸 扭曲发黄
His face, oddly enough, it looked almost yellow.
她是金发吗？
Was she blonde?
- 什么？  - 她有一头金发吗？
- Sorry?  - Did she have blonde hair?
噢 不 不 她是黑发
Oh, no, no. She had dark hair.
- 像我一样  - 嗯
- Like mine, then.  - Mm.
我是说 不是现在
I mean, not now.
是啊 像你一样
Yeah, like yours.
她当时多大？
How old was she?
她比我大两岁 当时是六二年
She was two years older than me, and that was '62.
嗯 那她当时大概二十七岁
Yeah, so she was about 27.
对
Yeah.
我妈妈是那年去世的
My mum died that year.
- 是吗？  - 是的 嗯
- Did she?  - Yeah. Mm.
- 我不知道为什么这很可笑但确实如此  - 可笑？
- I don't know why that's funny but it is.  - Funny?
唔 我们当时互相不认识 你和我
Well, we didn't know each other then, you and I,
但我们却同时经历着令人心碎的事 并且…
but we were both going through something really unpleasant, and...
我们相识了这么些年 还从没跟对方提起过
and yet we never talked about it in all the years that we've known each other.
- 从没  - 没有 从来没有
- Never.  - No. Never have.
我累了
I'm tired.
我要关灯吗？
Shall I turn off the light?
嗯
Yeah.
我也很累了
I'm quite tired, too.
星期二
过来
Come on.
麦克斯！
Max!
孩子！过来！
Yeah, boy! Come on!
过来！乖孩子
Come on! Good boy.
你今天起得真早
You're up early this morning.
是啊 我想我可能和你一起去镇上 如果你不介意的话
Yeah, I thought I might come into town with you, if you don't mind.
不 当然不介意
No, of course I don't mind.
我想去买个新的浮球阀
Yeah, I-I want to go to Thorns, get a new ballcock.
好啊
Oh, good.
你觉得我的图书馆卡还能用吗 凯特？
Do you think my library card will still be valid, Kate?
- 没什么不能用的啊  - 如果有时间的话我想去那转转
- I don't see why not.   - I might pop in there if there's time.
随便看看
Have a bit of a browse.
- 我们再一起吃个午饭  - 对 真棒
- We could have some lunch.  - Yeah, great.
呃 我有些自己的事情要做
Well, er, I'll just go do what I have to do.
你准备走了叫我就行
Give us a shout when you're ready.
好的
OK.
大概过一小时 我要打电话给花店 还有一两件事情要做
About an hour. I've got to call the florist and one or two things.
你觉得图书馆会有气候变化方面的书吗？
Do you think the library will have anything on climate change?
- 什么方面？  - 气候变化
- On what?  - Climate change.
- 抱歉我迟到了  - 没事
- Sorry I'm late.  - All right.
- 东西买到了吗？  - 什么东西？
- Did you get the thing?  - What thing?
- 浮球阀  - 呃 他们得先订货
- The ballcock.  - Er, they have to order it.
我过几天再去取
I'll pick it up in a few days.
你要吃点什么？
What do you want to eat?
我们该对环境问题多一点思考
We've got to think a lot more about the environment.
- 嗯… 我们有循环利用啊  - 有吗？
- Well, we recycle.  - Do we?
- 有 嗯 我会尽量 至少  - 是应该这样
- Yeah. Well, I try to, anyway.  - Well, we should.
你要是能来打扫空狗罐头然后丢到对应的垃圾桶里去就再好不过了
You're welcome to clean out the dog cans and put them in the right bins.
那些冰川的融冰量远远超出了人们的预想
Because these glaciers, they're melting a lot more than people imagined,
- 冰川融水不会顺流而下  - 那总要流向哪吧
- and the water's just not coming down.  - It's got to go somewhere.
不 它们会浸透岩层 然后从岩层底部开始 不断往上积聚
No, it's saturating into the rock beneath, and it's building up and up and up.
- 就像…  - 就像大坝
- L-Like...  - Like a dam.
就像大坝 对 不断堆积 填充 增长  然后…
Like a dam, yeah. It's waiting, waiting, waiting, and then...
哦
Oh.
毫无预警地
No warning.
就像海啸一样倾覆而下 所经之处横扫一空
Come down like a tsunami, wipe out everything in its path.
学校 教堂 咖啡馆喝咖啡的人
Schools, churches, people in cafes drinking their coffee,
钟表店里修理布谷鸟钟的老头
old men in shops tinkering with their cuckoo clocks.
要不是他们发现了她的尸体 那么她就要到那时候才会
And if they hadn't found her, that's when she'd have come down,
和岩石残骸一起被冲下来
with all the rock and debris.
那时候我们早就死了多少年了
We'll be long dead by then.
哦
Oh.
把书收起来
Put your book away.
哦 对
Oh, yeah.
- 你屏蔽了我的电话吗 凯特？  - 并没有
- You screening my calls, Kate?  - Not really.
- 你好  - 你好
- Hello.  - Hi.
- 莎莉！  - 你好 杰夫
- Sally!  - Hi, Geoff.
那是我最喜欢的一张
That's my favourite one, there.
好了 妈 已经看够了 有点没意思了
OK, Mum. I think it's enough now. It's getting really boring.
- 我为我的孙子骄傲  - 莎莉 我想看查理的照片
- I'm proud of my grandson.  - Sally, I want to have a look at Charley.
这几张太可爱了
These are so lovely.
照片拍的真美
And the photos are really beautiful.
- 是吧？  - 莎莉要成为摄影师呢
- Aren't they?  - Sally's going to be a photographer.
才没有 我只是去上了晚课 纯粹图好玩
I'm not. I'm just taking an evening course, just for the fun of it.
不是什么了不得的事
It's nothing grand.
- 但没准会有点成就  - 也可能不会有
- But it might lead to something.  - Or it might not.
我们拭目以待吧 好吗？不过你得在这上面下功夫才行
We shall see, won't we? But you should concentrate on it.
我大概三月前开始练习它
I took it up about three months ago.
这种乐器很容易学习 你能用尤克里里弹任何曲子
It's a good instrument to learn. You can play anything on the ukulele.
[乔治·福姆比：英国演员，时常弹奏尤克里里(夏威夷四弦琴)]
不光是乔治·福姆比的曲子 这很好 你知道我一直都讨厌他
It's not just George Formby, which is good because, as you know, I always hated him.
互联网真是太神奇了
The Internet is absolutely brilliant.
如果你去找一个叫“贾斯汀吉他网”的小伙子的话
If you go to a guy called justinguitars. com,
他真的教吉他 不过完全免费
he actually teaches guitar, but it's all free.
他也开始 呃 教尤克里里了
He's started, er, teaching ukulele as well.
再见 玩得开心
See you later. Have a nice time.
好的 再见
All right, see you later.
我觉得… 我觉得杰夫不会想去酒吧的
I don't think... I don't think Geoff wanted to go to the pub.
他要么去酒吧 要么就得和我们一起购物
It's either that or he comes shopping with us.
我们应该都去酒吧的
We could have gone to the pub, all of us.
看看他白天喝酒是什么样子
Know what he's like with daytime drinking.
他会没事的
Oh, he'll be all right.
不管怎样 他有了发泄的机会
Anyway, it gives him a chance to vent.
- 发泄什么？  - 关于你
- About what?  - About you.
妈！
Mum!
也不是说关于你 不过跟派对有关
Not about you as such, but about the party.
你说他要发泄跟派对有关的事… 是什么意思？
What do you mean about... vent about the party?
我想起乔治在我们的四十周年纪念前有多糟糕
When I think how awful George was before our 40th,
我差点就跟他离婚了
I was that close to divorcing him.
别管她
Ignore her.
那么 你打算穿什么礼服？你喜欢什么样的？
So, what's going to happen with your dress? What would you like?
所以 我们不该办派对吗？
So, should I not be having a party?
当然要有
Of course you should.
我们两个都很有压力
It is a lot of pressure for both of us.
而且不管怎样我都讨厌派对 就算是在最好的日子
And I hate parties anyway, at the best of times.
我说 我都从来没有开派对庆祝过自己的生日
I mean, I never even celebrate my birthday.
不 不 不 不 不 你得开
No, no, no, no, no, you have to.
我说 怪就怪在这儿
I mean, that's the strange thing.
乔治是很糟糕 但你记得他到了派对上的样子吗？
George was awful, but then do you remember him at the actual party?
他哭的有多厉害？
How much he cried?
还不仅仅是在致辞的时候哭
And not only during the speeches.
是啊 他是个很动情的人
Yeah, he was very sweet.
这就是为什么派对这种事情很重要
That's why these things are important.
什么 为了让丈夫们哭吗？
What, to make our husbands cry?
不光是丈夫们 所有的男人
Not just husbands, all men.
他们总是最先被触动的人
It's always them that break first.
莎莉的婚礼 查理的洗礼
Sally's wedding, Charley's christening.
我们能一起操办起来 是因为我们早就知道这些事情的重要性
We hold it together 'cause we already know how important these things are.
杰夫可不是爱哭鬼
Geoff is not much of a crier.
我打赌他在婚礼上哭了
I bet he cried at your wedding.
我不记得了
I don't remember.
如果这是某种进化的关键
If it's some twist of evolution
让男人们把一门心思花在讣告和分配遗产上
that needs men to be obsessed by their obituaries, their legacies,
那么或许我们的任务就是去敦促他们认清真正重要的是什么
then maybe it's ours to nudge them into realising what's really important
在他们用失望把自己给弄死之前 你知道的
before they kill themselves, you know, with the disappointment.
- 早安  - 哦
- Morning.  - Oh.
我打了个瞌睡
I nodded off.
你觉得莎莉的照片拍得怎么样？
What did you think of Sally's photos?
- 嗯？  - 莎莉的照片
- Mm?  - Sally's photos.
我觉得她的审美很不错
I think she's got a very good eye.
哦 没错 是这样
Oh, sure. Yeah. Mm.
嗯
Mm.
我有时候觉得没在屋子四面多挂一些照片真是可惜了
I sometimes think it's a shame not to have more photos around the house.
我们可以挂几幅上去
We could put some up.
但我们没有照片 没什么可挂的
Yeah, but we don't have any. Not really.
我是说 没有莉娜那种可以做成展览墙的照片
I mean, not like Lena does with her wall display.
我想是因为他们有儿子和孙子 而且…
I suppose it's because they've got children and grandchildren, and...
我们觉得拍自己的照片没什么意思
I guess we didn't see the point of taking pictures of ourselves.
感觉有点虚荣
Would have been a bit vain.
你之前说 每个无时无刻不在拍照的人
You used to say that everybody taking pictures all the time
都是在妨碍所有人的所有乐趣
stopped anyone having any fun.
- 我说过吗？  - 你说过
- Did I?  - You did.
- 听起来像是我说的话  - 嗯哼
- Sounds like something I'd say.  - Mm-hm.
你之前有过一部相机
You had a camera, once.
- 对 一台雅西卡  - 嗯 一台雅西卡
- Yeah, a Yashica.  - Mm, a Yashica.
是啊 我还留着呢
Yeah, I've still got it.
放在阁楼
It's in the loft.
不过现在我们老了再来看 这… 这真是可惜
Now that we're older, though, it... it's a shame.
你想要什么样的照片？
What would you want photos of?
- 麦克斯还是小狗那会儿的  - 嗯哼
- Max when he was a pup.  - Mm-hm.
在他之前的特莎
Tessa before him.
你在装饰克利瑟罗的那间屋子时把钉子钉到你手上的
You when you were decorating Clitheroe and you hammered that nail into your hand.
你想要那种照片？
You want a photograph of that?
哦 你知道我指的是什么
Oh, you know what I mean.
那是我们的第一所房子
It was our first house.
是的
It was.
那是我离开家后的第一个家
Yeah, it was my first home since leaving home,
自从离开父母 离开我的父亲
since leaving my parents, leaving my father.
我想我们那时还没有意识到
I suppose we don't realise at the time
但那些回忆…
but those memories...
… 它们就是最珍贵的事情 不是吗
...they're the things, aren't they?
我想要一张你在利兹麦加的照片
I'd want a picture of you at the Leeds Mecca.
那是我们相遇的地方
That's where we met.
你那时迷人的要命
You were a bloody knockout.
噢 有点别扭 不是吗
Oh, it's odd, isn't it,
回忆我们的曾经？
thinking of us back then?
我那时二十岁都不到 而你那么酷 嘴边叼着香烟
I wasn't even 20, and you were so cool, with your cigarette hanging in your mouth.
嗯
Mm.
我跟你说
Tell you what.
- 你在做什么？  - 过来
- What are you doing?  - Come on.
- 我们可以跳起来…  - 噢 讨厌！
- We can move the...  - Oh, bugger off!
来吧
Come on.
我可不会这么晚还在客厅跳起舞来
I'm not prancing around in the living room at this time of night.
手举起来 对
Over the top, yeah.
我们再也不是二十岁啦
We ain't 20 any more.
不是喽
No.
我们上楼去吧
Let's go upstairs.
我们来吧
Come on with ya.
希望你能让我印象深刻
Hope I can remember what you do.
我会让你好看的
I'll show you.
- 你下边怎么样了？  - 我觉得我来状态了
- How are you doing down there?  - I think I'm ready.
是吗？
Yeah?
- 你不用我换到上面来吗？  - 不 我快进来了
- You don't want me to go on top?  - No, I'm nearly there.
哦 没错
Oh, you are, too.
进来了
Oh, there you go.
噢 真棒
Oh, yeah.
哦
Oh.
亲一个
A kiss.
睁开眼
Open your eyes.
- 呃…  - 妈的
- Uh...  - Oh, shit.
噢 坏了
Oh, bugger.
- 我想我去了  - 我…
- I think I've lost it.  - I...
没事 没事 没事
OK, OK, OK.
杰夫 没关系的 没关系的
Geoff, it's OK, it's OK.
嘿
Hey.
- 唔…  - 没关系的
- Aw...  - It's OK.
我们睡觉吧
No, let's just go to sleep.
杰夫？
Geoff?
你在做什么？
What are you doing?
- 杰夫？  - 我很好 凯特
- Geoff?  - I'm OK, Kate.
拜托快下来 这太胡闹了
Please come down. This is ridiculous.
我没事
I'm OK.
你手里拿着的是什么？
What's that in your hand?
没什么
Nothing.
- 是她吗？  - 我发现了这个
- Is it her?  - I found it.
你不是发现了 你是半夜跑上去找它
You didn't find it. You went looking for it in the middle of the night
这根本不是一回事
and that's not the same thing at all.
- 让我看看  - 不
- Let me see it.  - No.
求你了 杰夫 我能看看吗？
Please, Geoff. Can I see it?
拜托 凯特 回床上去
Please, Kate, just go back to bed.
给我看看那该死的照片！
Show me the bloody picture!
只是一张照片 仅此而已
It's just a picture. It's all it is.
这并不意味着什么 只是一张他妈的照片
It doesn't mean anything. It's just a fucking picture.
谢谢
Thanks.
星期三
麦克斯！
Max!
来吧！
Come on!
周六你会找人给你化妆吗？
Are you getting someone to do your makeup on Saturday?
我还没想过这事
I wasn't thinking of it.
我认识一个女孩 她手法很厉害
I know this girl. She's very subtle.
你不用担心化妆后看起来像妓女
You wouldn't have to worry about looking like a hooker.
莎莉有个很好用的按摩器 可以去黑眼圈
Sally's got this amazing roll-on thing, zaps away dark circles.
我想你可以借来用用
I'm sure you could borrow it.
如果我看起来很疲惫的话 你可以直接跟我说
If I'm looking tired, you can just tell me.
你看起来很疲惫
You're looking tired.
我很好
I'm fine.
啊 这破天气
Ugh, this weather.
我告诉你乔治怎么说的
I'm just telling you what George said.
我不是要扫你的兴 真的 不是
I'm not trying to upset you. Really, I'm not.
我没觉得扫兴 你还没告诉我呢
I'm not upset, but you're not telling me anything.
你刚刚说杰夫情绪有点反常
You're just saying that Geoff was in a strange mood.
乔治他就是这么说的
That's what George said.
杰夫说了什么吗？
Did Geoff say anything?
比如？
Like what?
这正是我要问你的
That's what I'm asking you.
- 和派对有关？  - 不 和派对没关系
- About the party?  - No, not about the party.
他们在讨论政治
They were talking politics.
就这些？
That's it?
他有些咄咄逼人
Well, he was very aggressive.
唔 我想乔治能够替自己说话的
Well, I'm sure George can stand up for himself.
他表现得和之前一样
He was acting like he used to.
什么意思？
Meaning?
就像那次他在我生日上当着我所有朋友的面
Like that time he kept accusing me of being a fascist
一直指责我是法西斯主义者一样
in front of all my friends at my birthday
就因为我敢说撒切尔执政还不算太糟糕
just because I dared to say that Thatcher hadn't done such a bad job of it.
我说 我甚至都没投过她的票
I mean, I hadn't even voted for her.
这可不好玩 凯特
It wasn't funny, Kate.
不
No.
非常让人难堪
Very upsetting.
他还不停地行纳粹礼
He kept doing a Nazi salute.
好吧 这是有点好笑了
All right, it was a little bit funny.
哦 对不起
Oh, I'm sorry.
我不应该提起这回事的
I shouldn't have brought it up.
你知道杰夫是什么样子
You know what Geoff's like.
他对有些事情太过狂热了
He gets over-passionate about things.
我想这就是你爱上他的原因
I suppose that's why you fell in love with him.
是啊
Yes.
哦 还有另外一件事
Oh, er, there's another thing.
什么？
What?
杰夫说他不确定他会想去工作午餐
Geoff says he's not sure that he wants to go to the works lunch.
克劳利家的吗？
At Crawley's?
- 可就在明天了  - 我知道
- But it's tomorrow.  - I know.
而且这次聚会很早就开始准备了
And it's been organised for so long.
乔治还期待着要把老朋友们都叫到一起来 但如果…
George was looking forward to getting the old gang together but if...
那他说为什么了吗？
Well, did he say why?
没有说
Don't think so.
我去跟他说
I'll speak to him.
呃 也许这没什么大不了的
Er, maybe it doesn't matter.
不 我去跟他说
No, I'll speak to him.
女士们…
Ladies...
倒满吗？
Full, full?
还要加点牛奶吗？
Do you want more milk?
好的
Yes.
来点饼干？不要了吗？
Biscuit? No?
不要？
No?
那我把饼干放这儿 我自己要拿一块吃
Well, I'll leave them there. And I'll take one.
- 谢谢你  - 在这之后
- Thank you.  - After that,
商人们通过这条新开辟的航线进行生意往来
the merchants used these newly created waterways,
航道被逐年加深拓宽
and over the years they were cut deeper and wider,
这就是为什么布罗茨会成为今天的面貌
and this is why the Broads are as they are today
供大家欣赏
for all of you to enjoy.
试想一下如果罗马人在别处发现了泥炭
Now, just imagine if those Romans had found peat elsewhere
或是决定在国土上的其它地方开挖泥炭
or chosen to dig in another part of the country.
那这些航道也就不会存在了
Then these broads wouldn't be here at all.
那是杰夫吗？
Is that Geoff?
是的 是他
Yes, it is, yeah.
他在做什么？
What's he doing?
他又抽烟了吗？
Is he smoking again?
看上去是
Looks like it.
在派对那天之前你该让他把胡子刮了
You should get him to shave before the big day too.
- 你好 杰夫里  - 你好 莉娜
- Hello, Geoffrey.  - Hello, Lena.
希望你已经准备好你的致辞了
Hope you've got your speech prepared.
我想在星期六听到你赞美凯特的话
I want to hear nice things about Kate on Saturday.
我听说你不想去克劳利家吃午餐
So, I hear you don't want to go to the Crawley's lunch.
你不去没关系 但我想知道原因
I don't mind if you don't, but I wondered why.
我就是不想去
I just don't.
你一直都很期待和大家再次碰面啊
You've been looking forward to seeing everyone again.
这件事你都念叨好几个星期了
You've been talking about it for weeks.
- 为什么不想去了？  - 我有我的原因
- Why don't you want to go?  - I've got me reasons.
什么原因？
Which are?
我去不去跟你有什么关系？
Why does it matter to you if I go or not?
和我没关系 但都已经安排好了
It doesn't, but it's been arranged.
所以呢？
So?
所以你不能言而无信 仅仅因为你不想去做
So you can't just back out of things simply because you don't feel like it.
即使你有你的原因
Even when you have reasons.
乔治他也会很不开心的
And George will be very upset.
他… 他好几周前就开始计划这次聚会了
He's... well, he's been organising it for weeks.
- 他是你的朋友  - 喔 好吧
- And he's your friend.  - Oh, fine.
- 那你会去吗？  - 我就是那么说的 不是吗？
- Then you'll go?  - Well, that's what I said, didn't I?
有些天 我们完全忘掉了去意大利事 停滞不前
Some days, we forgot all about getting to Italy. Just stayed put.
我们变得漫不经心
We were being heedless.
这是我能找到的最合适的词
I think that's the word I'm looking for.
漫不经心？
Heedless?
漫不经心
Heedless.
在她的家乡 柏林墙正被筑起
Back in her Berlin, the Wall was going up
[猪湾事件：美国阴谋以武力支持古巴流亡者颠覆古巴革命政权]
而在美国刚发生了猪湾事件
and in America we'd just had the Bay of Pigs.
但那会儿 我们根本不管那些
But up there, we weren't thinking about all that.
也不去想我们的未来
Weren't thinking about our future.
但与此同时 我们也根本没有漫不经心
But, at the same time, we weren't heedless at all.
你怎么可能漫不经心？当你清楚自己的目标时
How can you be when, when you know what your purpose is?
当每一天似乎都有着某种意义时
When every day seems to have some point to it.
寻找安顿之处 寻找食物
Finding somewhere to stay, finding food.
那些日子里我们哪儿都没去
And the days we didn't go anywhere,
但它们就是好像充满了目标
they seemed just as purposeful
就像在该死的清晨四点雄赳赳地启程那样
as when we set out in complete seriousness at four in the fucking morning.
我想 嗯… 我想衰老最可怕的地方莫过于
I-I think, um... I think that's the worst part of getting decrepit,
失去那种… 目的性
losing that... purposefulness.
今天我想起了我们之前看到过的那些花儿
I-I was remembering today how we used to see these flowers.
紫罗兰的一种吧 我想是的
Some sort of violet, I think they were.
它们会找到一小块雪融掉的草地
They'd find a patch of grass where the snow had melted
然后就茁壮成长
and they'd just spring up.
我知道它们只是花朵 但它们看上去那么坚定
I know they were only flowers, but they seemed so determined.
甚至可以说 勇敢
Brave, even.
我觉得卡佳和我就是那样
And that's how I see Katya and me.
游走四方 摒弃现代文明
Wandering around, turning our backs on civilization.
勇敢？
Brave?
可以这么说
In a way.
你不觉得吗？
Don't you think?
并不
Not really.
为什么不？
Why not?
我说 你们究竟在干什么？
I mean, what were you actually doing?
你们只是在爬某座该死的山罢了
You're just climbing up some bloody mountain.
当然 我不是说我们这么做是出于勇敢
Well, I'm not saying what we did was out of bravery.
我觉得 你只是在追一个想要被追的女孩而已
I think you were just chasing a girl who wanted to be chased.
你不了解她
You didn't know her.
是
No.
我不了解
I didn't.
我累了
I'm tired
睡之前我想问你个问题
I want to ask you something before we go to sleep.
什么问题？
What's that?
如果她没死 如果你们到了意大利
If she hadn't died, if you had got to Italy,
那你会真的娶她吗？
would you have married her for real?
但我们没能到意大利 不是吗？
But we didn't get to Italy, did we?
而且她确实死了
And she did die.
嗯 但是如果呢
Yeah, but if you had.
我以为你不喜欢这种假设的问题
I thought you didn't like theoretical questions.
只管回答我
Just answer me.
是的
Yes.
是 你就会娶她？
Yes, you would have married her?
是的
Yes.
我就会娶她 她就会嫁给我
We would have married each other.
我觉得我再也没法谈论她的事了
I don't think I can talk about her any more.
我知道我说过可以 但现在我办不到
I know I said I could, but I can't.
星期四
那边还有你认识的人吗？
Anyone you know still there?
什么？没了 都是新人
What? No, they're all new.
好吧 那 过会儿见
OK, then, I'll see you later.
嗯
Yeah.
等等
Hang on.
试着让自己开心点
Just try and enjoy yourself today.
嗯 我尽量
Yeah. I'll try.
麦克斯 闭嘴！
Max, shut up!
噢…
Oh...
喂
Hello.
- 梅瑟夫人？  - 是的 我是
- Mrs Mercer?  - Yes, it is.
你好 我是DJ乔治
Hi, it's George the DJ.
噢 是的 我准备打给你的
Oh, yes, I-I meant to call you.
呃 歌？噢 选歌 对
Er, song? Oh, songs, yes.
呃… 稍等一下
Er... just a minute.
- 海龟乐队的《Happy Together》  - 好的 好品味
- Happy Together by The Turtles.  - OK, good choice.
布法罗·斯普林菲尔德的《For What It's Worth》
For What It's Worth by Buffalo Springfield.
马文·盖伊的《Your Precious Love》
Um, Your Precious Love by Marvin Gaye.
还有《Higher And Higher》…
And Higher And Higher by...
我不记得谁唱的了
I don't remember who that's by.
是杰基·威尔逊吗？
Is it Jackie Wilson?
- 是的  - 对
- Yeah.  - Yeah.
- 用埃尔顿·约翰的《Your Song》怎么样？  - 不 不用埃尔顿·约翰
- What about Your Song by Elton John?  - No. No Elton John.
其他的？我还没列好歌单
What else? I-I haven't got my list.
忧郁布鲁斯的？
The Moody Blues?
够了
That's enough.
第一支舞用哪首歌？
What about your first dance?
派特斯的《Smoke Gets In Your Eyes》
Smoke Gets In Your Eyes by The Platters.
好的 谢谢 非常感谢 再见
Yeah, thank you. Thank you so much. Goodbye.
怎么样？
How was it?
真他妈没完没了
Fucking endless.
你他妈肯定不会相信 他们对那地方做了什么
You wouldn't fucking believe what they've done to the place.
全部都流水线化了
It's all been streamlined.
我在世上的第一份工作已经不复存在了
My first job on the floor doesn't exist any more.
告诉你 要是我还在管理层的话 我是决不会让它发生的
I tell you, if I was still in management, I wouldn't have let that happen.
还有工会 他们屁都不放一个
And the unions, they don't give a shit.
当然 也许他们放了 但没人在意
Well, maybe they do and nobody takes any notice.
而且 当年的小孩子们都老成什么样啦 一点都不体面
A-And how the lads have descended into old age, it's not pretty.
还有乔治 一直在摆弄他那该死的尤克里里
And there's George, wanging on about his fucking ukulele.
最糟糕的是 大家都好像很感兴趣的样子
The worst part of it is that they all seemed interested.
还有莱恩 他在阿尔加维买了套别墅
And Len, he's got a villa on the Algarve.
你还记得“红莱恩”吗？
Do you remember Red Len?
我们以前都叫他“列宁”
We used to call him Len-in,
现在他满口都是在他妈的阿尔加维打高尔夫的事
and now all he can talk about is playing golf on the Al-fucking-garve
跟他的银行家孙子一起
with his grandson, who's a banker.
嗯 嗯
Mm. Mm.
我日！
Fuck me!
星期五
[我自己坐公交去镇上了，抱歉！]
有谁想要这周的Big Issue吗？
Would anybody like one, this week's Big Issue?
您想看看这周的Big Issue吗？
Could I interest you in a Big Issue?
有谁想要这周的Big Issue吗？
Would anybody like one, this week's Big Issue?
下午好 您现在有空吗？
Good afternoon, love. Spare a couple of minutes?
我想向您介绍一下我们正在做的这个慈善项目
I'd love to tell you a bit about this charity we've got going on.
呃 我不感兴趣
Um, I'm not interested.
是吗？打搅了
No? No problem.
我能帮您吗？
Can I help you?
- 我能坐吗？  - 当然 请坐
- May I sit down?  - Yeah, please do.
- 您想去哪儿旅游呢？  - 不 我…
- Is there somewhere you have in mind?  - No, I...
我想问下有没有一个男人来过这里
I want to know if a man has been in here.
他是我丈夫
It's my husband.
我们向你咨询过几次 我想知道他有没有来过
We've used you a few times and I wondered if he'd been in.
他是不是在问去瑞士的事？
Um, was he enquiring about Switzerland?
- 这么晚啊   - 是的 抱歉
- Been a long time.  - Yeah, sorry.
我去了…
I've been...
唔 市里真是太堵了 回来的巴士也是… 抱歉
Well, town was very busy and the bus back was... Sorry.
我今天去了旅行社
I went to the travel agent today.
- 什么？  - 我今天去了旅行社
- What?  - I went to the travel agent.
你准备去瑞士吗？
Are you going to Switzerland?
- 不 不是   - 为什么？
- No. I'm not.  - Why not?
要是不走一会儿歇一会儿我连… 我连去村里都走不到
Well, I can't walk to the village without... without sitting down.
我要怎么爬一座他妈的山啊？
How am I going to climb a fucking mountain?
那就是你不去的理由吗？
And that's the reason?
不 凯特 不是因为那个
No, Kate, that's not the reason.
因为如果你真的要去 而我…
Because if you do go, and if I...
噢 天呐 凯特 这跟卡佳没关系
Oh, Christ, Kate. This isn't about Katya.
请别再说她的名字了
Please, stop saying her name.
- 我受不了  - 这跟… 这跟卡佳没关系
- I can't bear it.  - It isn't... It isn't about Katya.
有关系
It is.
当然有关系
Of course it is.
就像我发现了充斥着这栋房子的气味到底是什么一样
Like me discovering what this smell is around the house.
- 别这样  - 她的香水味 是吧？
- Oh, please.  - And it's her perfume, OK?
好像她这会儿就站在屋子角一样
It's like she's been standing in the corner of the room all this time,
- 就站在我身后  - 噢 别这样
- behind my back.  - Oh, come on.
这味道污染了所有东西
And it's tainted everything.
我们所有的决定 去哪里度假 读什么书
All our decisions, where we go on holiday, what books we read,
养哪种狗 听什么歌
what dog you want to choose, what music we want to listen to.
在那些大事上也一样
And the big things, too.
尤其是那些大事
Especially the big things.
她跟那一切都没有任何关系
She's had nothing to do with any of that.
我倒是想告诉你我正在想的… 所有事情
I'd like to be able to tell you everything I'm... thinking,
和我知道的所有事情
and everything I know,
但我做不到
but I can't.
这你能理解吗？
Do you understand that?
嗯
Yeah.
是的 我理解
Yes, I do.
现在我只希望 你能来明天的聚会
All I want now is for you to just come to the party tomorrow.
- 我当然会来的  - 我真的需要你发自内心地想去
- Of course I'm going to come.  - I really need you to want to be there.
是的 我是真的想去那儿
Yes, I do want to be there.
因为我一个人明白我一直都无法让你满足
Because it's one thing me knowing I haven't been enough for you.
和…
It's something...
… 让其他人也都察觉到这一点 就完全不一样了
...altogether different that everyone else feels it, too.
你真的认为你无法让我满足吗？
You really believe you haven't been enough for me?
不 我认为我足以让你满足了
No. I think I was enough for you.
我只是不确定你怎么想
I'm just not sure you do.
啊 凯特
Ah, Kate.
那可真糟糕
That's terrible.
- 今天吃药了吗？  - 没有
- Have you taken your pills today?  - No.
那我去拿来
Then I'm going to get them.
然后我们吃晚饭 然后我们上床睡觉
And then we're going to have dinner, and then we're going to go to bed.
然后我们准备起床
And then we're going to get up
然后我们重新来过
And we'll try and start again.
没问题 凯特 我能做到的
OK, Kate, I can do that.
我们能做到的
We can do that.
我保证
I promise.
星期六
早上好
Morning.
我给你泡了茶
I made you some tea
- 噢  - 还有 呃…
- Oh.  - And, er. .
我把厕所给修好了 还没有切掉手指
I've managed to fix the lavatory without cutting me finger off.
现在是不是有点晚了？
Is it late?
是的 我在想着要炒个蛋
Y-Yeah, I thought I'd make us some scrambled eggs
然后我们带麦克斯出去走走
and then we can take Max for a walk.
- 好极了  - 是的
- Great.  - Right.
就这样吧
Will do.
我们还有鸡蛋呢 是吧？
Yeah, we have got some eggs, haven't we?
我在这看到过一只旋木雀 可爱的小家伙
I saw a treecreeper here, once, a lovely little bird.
有人告诉我 它们先飞到树底部 然后爬上去觅食
Somebody told me that they fly down to the bottom of the tree and work their way up.
而五子雀呢 它们先飞到顶上 然后再爬下来
And nuthatches, they fly to the top of the trunk, work their way down.
乖 乖 好孩子
Come on. Come on. Good boy.
- 你以前很喜欢观察鸟类  - 是啊 没错
- You used to love your birdwatching.  - I did, yes.
可笑的是你都忘记这些给你带来快乐的事了
It's funny how you forget the things in life that make you happy.
在这呆好 麦克斯
Stay there, Max.
我找到了 麦克斯
Found it, Max.
抱歉 这次我又没给你买任何东西
Again, I'm sorry I didn't get you anything.
噢 别犯傻了
Oh, don't be silly.
这项链很漂亮
This is very beautiful.
我很高兴你喜欢
I'm glad you like it.
我想过要给你买块表
I was going to get you a watch.
我还想在上面刻字 可是不知道该写什么
I was thinking of having it engraved, but I wasn't sure what to write.
我喜欢不知道时间的感觉
I like not knowing the time.
- 我就是做不到  - 是的
- I just couldn't do it.  - No.
- 别担心 亲爱的 不一定非要做  - 大多数人都不想的
- Don't worry, darling, you don't have to.  - Most people don't want to.
跟我来下好吗？我有东西给你看
Will you come with me? I've got something to show you.
不要惊喜 莉娜 我不想要惊喜
No surprises, Lena. I don't want a surprise.
- 哇  - 是不是棒极了？
- Wow.  - Isn't it wonderful?
看看这 是的
Look at this. Yes.
- 莉娜 那是什么？  - 过来看看吧
- Lena, what's that?  - Ah, come and have a look.
哇
Wow.
是照片
Photos.
- 都是从谁那儿弄来的？  - 我到处打电话 每个人都贡献了一些
- Where did they all come from?  - I rang round. Everyone contributed.
大多是我的
Most of them are mine.
看呐 凯特 看看你多美
Look, Kate, look how beautiful you are.
凯特 这是特莎还是只小狗的时候
Kate, there's Tessa when she was a puppy.
啊 那是我… 带着护目镜 在割草
Ah, there's me... me and me goggles, strimming.
割草呢
Strimming.
- 看看这里的我们 还记得吗？  - 埃及
- Look at us there. Remember that?  - Egypt.
是的 我们去埃及的时候
Yeah, when we went to Egypt.
真漂亮 咱俩
Gorgeous, we both are.
莉娜 这真是棒极了 谢谢你
Lena, this is wonderful. Thank you.
对一个老法西斯来说还不赖 哈？
Not bad for an old fascist, huh?
简直棒极了
Yeah, not bad at all.
- 我等不及要听你的演讲了  - 都记在这呢
- Oh, I can't wait to hear your speech.  - Yeah, it's all in here.
- 那大家可都有麻烦了  - 是啊 尤其是你
- Ugh, we're all in trouble then.  - Yeah, especially you.
你就等着看他哭鼻子吧
Just you wait for those tears.
- 那是谁？  - 我想是亚瑟
- Who's that?  - That's Arthur, I think.
- 是的 就是他  - 是的
- Yes, it is.  - Yes.
- 是 是亚瑟 几年前了  - 看看还有谁呢？
- Yeah, it's Arthur, a few years ago.  - And who else do I see?
女士们 先生们 下面是大家共同期盼的时刻
Ladies and gentlemen, the moment you've all been waiting for.
有请… 杰弗里·梅瑟先生
I give you... Mr Geoffrey Mercer.
快点 杰弗里
Go on, Geoffrey.
能听见我吗？
Now, can you hear me?
- 能听见  - 是的
- We can hear you.  - Yes.
噢 乖乖
Oh, dear.
那我得试着好好讲话了
I'd better try and make sense, then.
好吧 首先 我想感谢大家 来到今晚的聚会
Well, I'd like to thank you all, first off, for being here this evening.
你们也许还记得 几年前 呃… 我的心脏搭桥手术
Some of you may recall that, er... my bypass,
呃 在几年前抢尽了风头 嗯 总之就是这样
er, upstaged things a few years ago, so, anyway, there we are.
现在 我不太习惯做这样的发言
Now, er, I-I'm not used to making this kind of speech
在 呃… 这样的场合
on this, er... sort of occasion,
但是… 总之…
but, er... well...
我会尽力的
I-I'll give it me best shot.
随着 嗯 随着我们变老
A-As, um, as we get older,
我们好像不再 呃 做出选择
we seem to stop, er, making choices.
至少 呃 不再做出重大的选择
Big ones, er, anyway.
也许我们一生中面临的选择 呃 只有那么多
Perhaps we only get so many, er, in a lifetime,
一旦我们用尽 呃 它们就不再有了
and once we've used them up, er, they're gone.
又或许是我们的大脑 也变老了 呃 还患上了关节炎
Or maybe our brains, they just get a bit, er, old and arthritic,
就像… 就像乔治的膝盖一样
like, er... like George's knee.
呃 不论如何
Er, whatever.
结果就是 我们年轻的时候做出的那些选择
The upshot is that the choices we make when we're young
都相当非常重要
are pretty bloody important.
呃 就像… 就像我跟凯特 所做出的这个选择
Er, like... like the choice, er, Kate and me made
在四十五年前的… 今天
45 years ago... today.
今天
Today.
现在 生活… 生活并不总是 嗯… 一帆风顺
Now, things... things haven't always been, er... idyllic.
呃 就像所有的夫妻一样 我们也经历过低谷 呃… 也经历过高峰
Er, like all couples, we've had our downs as, er... as well as our ups.
我们所有人 我们所有人 都认为…
We all, we all, er, think...
我们都希望我们在某些事情上所做的是另一种选择
W-We all wish we'd done some things, er, differently,
希望我们未曾犯下某些错误
wish we hadn't made certain mistakes,
但是… 随便了
but, er... whatever.
我不得不说 我也必须说
I have to say, and I need to say,
说服你 嫁给我 凯特
that persuading you, er, to marry me, er, Kate,
是我做过的最棒的事
was the best thing I've ever done.
嗯 顺便一提 我还真花了点功夫
Er, it took some doing, by the way.
是的 你父亲 我觉得他有点不中意
Yeah, so your father, I-I don't think he was convinced
认为我不是你最理想的对象
I was the greatest catch in the world.
我很好奇为什么不是
I wonder why that was.
不过总之 呃 说服你嫁给我
But anyway, er, persuading you to marry me
是我做过的最棒的事了
was the best thing I've ever done,
还有 我很抱歉 真的很抱歉
and, er, I'm sorry, I-I truly am,
就是 你并不… 你并不总是知道
that, er, you haven't, er... you haven't always known that
因为 嗯 对我来说 凯特
because, er, well, for me, Kate,
这就是 这就是关于… 关于一切 关于所有的这些
this is, er, this is what it's... what it's all about, what all this is about,
为什么所有… 为什么所有朋友们今晚都来到了这里
why all... why all our friends are here this evening.
那就是 嗯… 因为你和我
It's about, er... it's about you and me.
你和我 凯特
You and me, Kate.
我们
Us.
是的
Yeah.
我觉得 老实说… 这就是所有… 我要说的话
And I think, really, that's about all I've, er... got to say
还有这个… 我爱你
except that, er... l love you.
我真的很爱你
I love you very much.
谢谢你这么多年来陪伴在我身边
And thank you for standing by me through all these years
忍受我的胡闹 还有… 希望我们能天长地久
and putting up with all my nonsense, and, er... long may it continue.
敬杰夫和凯特！
Geoff and Kate!
杰夫和凯特！
他的发言棒极了 不是吗？
It was fantastic. Wasn't it?
真的
It was.
现在…
And now...
两位爱人请上前来 跳第一只舞吧？
...would the two lovebirds kindly take to the floor for the first dance?
在座有谁不知道 或者那时尚未出生的诸位
And for those of you that don't know, or weren't alive,
这首歌正是四十五年前的今天放的那首歌
this is the very same song that was played 45 years ago today.
下面有请梅瑟夫妇
I give you Mr and Mrs Mercer.
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke Gets In Your Eyes ♪
♫ 人们曾经问我怎知 ♫
♪ They asked me how I knew ♪
♫ 我的爱情意真挚 ♫
♪ My true love was true ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 我理直气壮地回答 ♫
♪ I of course replied ♪
♫ 内心深处的感情 ♫
♪ Something here inside ♪
♫ 是无法否认的 ♫
♪ Cannot be denied ♪
♫ 他们说总有一天你会发现 ♫
♪ They said some day you'll find ♪
♫ 恋爱中的人都是盲目的 ♫
♪ All who love are blind ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 当你热情澎湃的时候 ♫
♪ When your heart's on fire ♪
♫ 你才会意识到 ♫
♪ You must realise ♪
♫ 你的眼睛蒙上了一层烟雾 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 我嘲笑他们 这令我发笑 ♫
♪ So I chaffed them and I gaily laughed ♪
♫ 想到他们竟怀疑我的爱 ♫
♪ To think they could doubt our love ♪
♫ 如今我的爱人离我而去 ♫
♪ Yet today, my love has flown away ♪
♫ 我终于失去了我的爱 ♫
♪ I' I am without my love ♪
♫ 失去了我的爱 ♫
♪ Without my love ♪
♫ 饱受朋友的讥笑 ♫
♪ Now laughing friends deride ♪
♫ 伤心的泪水再也隐藏不住 ♫
♪ Tears I cannot hide ♪
♫ 噢 ♫
♪ 0h! ♪
♫ 我只能强颜欢笑地说 ♫
♪ When a lovely flame dies ♪
♫ 当爱情的火焰熄灭时 ♫
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的眼 ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your eyes ♪
♫ 烟雾沉醉了你的… ♫
♪ Smoke gets in your... ♪
♫ 眼 ♫
♪ Eyes ♪
♫ 我们已经说了 ♫
♪ We've already said ♪
45周年
♫ 再见 ♫
♪ Goodbye ♪
♫ 既然你一定要离开 ♫
♪ Since you've got to go ♪
♫ 噢 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now, go now ♪
♫ 在你看见我哭泣之前 ♫
♪ Before you see me cry ♪
♫ 我不想你告诉我 ♫
♪ I don't want you to tell me ♪
♫ 你现在想要做什么 ♫
♪ Just what you intend to do now ♪
♫ 因为 我得告诉你多少次 ♫
♪ 'Cause how many times do I have to tell you ♪
♫ 亲爱的 亲爱的 我现在依然爱你？♫
♪ Darling, darling, I'm still in love with you now? ♪
♫ 我们已经说了… ♫
♪ We've already said... ♪
♫ “再见” ♫
♪ "So long" ♪
♫ 我不想看见你离开 ♫
♪ I don't want to see you go ♪
♫ 喔 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now Go now ♪
♫ 你连试都不要试 ♫
♪ Don't you even try ♪
♫ 告诉我你并不想这样离开 ♫
♪ Telling me that you really don't want me to end this way ♪
♫ 因为 亲爱的 亲爱的 ♫
♪ 'Cause, darling, darling ♪
♫ 你难道看不出我想要你留下？♫
♪ Can't you see I want you to stay? ♪
♫ 啊 ♫
♪ Yeah ♪
♫ 既然你一定要离开 ♫
♪ Since you've got to go ♪
♫ 噢 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ Oh, you'd better go now ♪
♫ 去吧 去吧 去吧 ♫
♪ Go now, go now Go now ♪
♫ 在你看见我哭泣之前 ♫
♪ Before you see me cry ♪
♫ 我不想你告诉我 ♫
♪ I don't want you to tell me ♪
♫ 你现在想要做什么 ♫
♪ Just what you intend to do now ♪
♫ 因为 我得告诉你多少次 ♫
♪ 'Cause how many times do I have to tell you ♪
♫ 亲爱的 亲爱的 我现在依然很爱你 ♫
♪ Darling, darling, I'm still in love ♪
♫ 依然很爱你 ♫
♪ Still in love with you now ♪
♫ 我不想看见你离开 ♫
♪ I don't want to see you go ♪
♫ 可是亲爱的 你最好现在就离开 ♫
♪ But, darling, you'd better go now ♪